this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello this is Adam Gordon Bell
for software engineering radio today I'm
speaking with Johnathan baccaro author
of the legacy code programmers toolbox
Jonathan has been a C++ developer for
eight years his focus is on writing
expressive code and working with legacy
code
welcome to software engineering radio
Jonathan thanks thanks for having me so
today we will be talking about skills
for working with legacy code
we have a previous episode number 295
with Michael feathers that also touches
on this subject but let's start with
some definitions so can you define
legacy code right now I think several
definitions out there but all have in
common that thing that it's negative
thing it's essentially existing code
that's hard to work with so that's
that's essentially the gist of it
now since say yeah I wrote a book on how
to work with legacy code I had to come
up with a more precise definition so my
definition would be threefold first it's
code that's hard to understand for you
second it's code that you're not
comfortable changing n and three it's
code that you're somehow concern with so
that's my definition I try to to define
it as close as possible to to something
like of the colloquial term that people
use in the day-to-day life legacy code
now there are other definitions out
there like for example Michaels Michael
feathers which you just mentioned we
just mentioned Michael defines legacy
code as code without tests and some
people have other definitions and some
vague definitions include like the code
that was there before I got in my
company for example
something you can hear so yeah it's it's
all around the same the same theme
really it's Co that's existing that's
already there and that you have to work
with them that's not easy to work with I
think that matches my intuition of what
I what I think people mean when they say
legacy code so in in terms of Michael's
definition with tests do you feel that
there's cases where that doesn't fit
where code has tests and instill as
legacy code or vice versa well I think
it's a pretty good definition now of
course although yeah I think there are
some cases where there are tests but you
still it would be too hard to understand
like when you actually get into the code
that is tested although you wouldn't be
so much comfortable changing because how
but because of how it's written and you
know when we talk about tests I think
this definition of tests means unit
tests which are automatic tests like
it's it's code that is testing some
other code so so you write that kind of
yeah code and you run it's often so that
you go you've got a quick feedback in
regular feedback about whether or not
you broke something so that's a unit
test but when you write unit tests you
have to write an off test to have enough
coverage to be confident with your
legacy code and be more comfortable
changing so I guess you know you have
some curse that has some code that has
some tests as some tests that are not
relevant and and you wouldn't be so
comfortable changing it how much how
much legacy code do you think is out
there oh I think quite a lot like
millions and millions of clients code
for sure legacy code is everywhere I
don't think I've met anyone who doesn't
have to deal with legacy code in a
substantial portion of his work at least
from I remember I think the the people
that do have to deal with legacy core
legacy code are perhaps students or
people that do programming as a hobby in
that case you are in full control you
probably wrote all or most of the code
and there's not so much to do with that
at the same time so it's still
manageable so for students and hobbyist
I guess that we be close to zero upset
but for professional developers it's
everywhere I don't know perhaps I know
like 95% just as a sake of not seeing a
hundred percent but as it's like yeah
very very substantial bit that would be
my my rough estimate so in your
experience you mentioned you know
students would be people who might not
interact with it is is coming to terms
with dealing with legacy code an
important skill that the developers have
to build as they enter the professional
world yeah it's like a crucial it's a
coral let's go with have when you think
about it when you get into a new job
like a few it's not your fertile but
something get you probably gonna get
into an existing project and perhaps
this project or company has been there
for years and and some other people have
worked on it perhaps quite a lot of
other people and so on your first day
you're gonna be thrown into that huge
sea of code written by perhaps thousands
or more of people over years so you have
to be able to work with that somehow you
know it's funny because I was I was
browsing through the episodes of SU
radio there's one that I haven't had
time to catch up with which is by Adam
bar which you interviewed about bad code
and Adam has written a book it's called
the problem with software why small
engineers write bad code haven't read
the book yet and haven't listened to
I've just isn't the beginning of the
interview and my impression of what I
was saying is that we tend we as a
community even though there are some
very smart people tend to write code
that's not so good so when you enter a
company chances are you're going to have
to face some code that's not as easy to
work with us as you would wish it were
so yeah that's a an essential thing
because you
that's what out there and you have to do
something with it
yeah it is a great interview by the way
I listen to it and it's really
informative if we're if we're in this
role how to
develop an understanding of a legacy
code base that were thrown into there
are quite a few ways I think to
understand legacy codes I think there
are a few different scales really it
would be interesting to have a global
overview knowing where as well and also
being able to read the code like you
would read English you know so that I
think there's these are the two scales
you want develop that quite a few ways
to each one I talked a lot about that in
my my book but if we can pick a few for
each if that answered the question but
let's say for having a global view you
can rely on call stacks you know you're
like a call stack is sort of some sort
of like slice of a program for a running
program a program is essentially
composed of function calling other
functions or calling objects may have
methods and and sometimes function
causing another function that calls
another function and so on and so forth
in an in peacoat basic basis that'd be
quite a few layers and all piled up that
forms a stack and that's called a call
stack so what I'm saying is that you can
it's interesting to to read stacks like
you pick a stack in your running program
and see what's in there now there are I
know like perhaps an infinity not
that much like ridiculous amount of
stacks you can you can look at any
program so have to know how to choose
your course tax a good call stack an
informative course tank in my opinion is
the core stack that's both deep and that
means that that's high as a stack and in
a typical use case of the application
now how do you find such a call stack I
mean a deep one in a one that with a
typical use case well the thing to do is
to find a typical use case and finding a
typical use case well that's something
that's easier to do like you can ask the
business people like they can call
clients if you have access to them ask
them what they do like what they like
doing with your application and you
don't have your to go use case or worse
come to author so you can
the dog documentation saying what
awesome things your application is doing
you can find use case probably easier
than you can find somebody who's
knowledgeable about the code so that
would be to have like one technique to
have a global view and and starting to
see how big chunks of code interact with
each other
so you would find a typical use case and
put a breakpoint in there somewhere
and then you're looking through the call
stack and so the idea is that this will
give you an idea of how how things are
called at a high level that's right and
that would be a typical use case and
preferably a deep one so that you can
see a lot of layers so this gives a
high-level view of things is there a
point at which we should start digging
into the actual code yeah at some point
you have to anyway I mean our job is
working with codes so at some point you
have to read code I mean reading code is
what we do really most of our time as
software developers so yeah you sooner
than later you have to read some code
and you're presented with that piece of
text really source code and you have to
make some sounds sense out of it and
sometimes you have to read quite a lot
of code because like you're searching on
something for example when you're trying
to figure out like this massive function
or big object or several function that
work together whatever so you have to
read codes and if you want to be able to
produce anything in a reasonable time
and keeping the thing interesting and
not boring and you have to read to be
able to read code fast and reading fast
is cool it's not magic it's not reserved
to you know I can delete something it's
a school and anyone can I can have it
reading code fast and in my book I take
inspiration from how to read a book fast
like a like pros that are techniques to
be a fast reader of a book or to be like
a speed reader and one of them is for
example to go for the places that tend
to contain the inn
formation in a book it happens that the
information is at the beginning and at
the end most of it like the gist of it
and that's apparently true for most
books and that's also true within a book
like in a given chapter at the beginning
you have like an overview at the end you
have like another overview and that's
where you can get most of the
information and the rest is more like
details and that's true for a section
and that's referred paragraph in there
parently that's true in a book and I
think that's also true for code and I
think that good places to look for
information is at the beginning and at
the end and the beginning is something
that you is quite natural to read
because like you tend to start with the
beginning
I can want to figure out what this
function is doing and you start reading
it from the beginning
so yeah that's something that's quite
natural all right what I say is start
reading the end is also interesting and
I advocate that you should start by
reading the end what early what's the
advantage of starting reading a function
from the end well when you think about
say the purpose of function is to do
something if I can be actually doing
something like performing an effect or
it can be computing something and
returning it so the function is written
for something and or the body of the
function is typically oriented towards
producing that goal and that goal is
likely towards the end like for example
if your function has a classical pattern
of returning something and the law
storage function is return whatever then
you know but reading the last nine up
all the purpose of that function is to
return that thing so for instance if you
look at the end and see that it returns
like a file descriptor then you would be
able to read it knowing that that it has
something to do with figuring out what
file to return is that the idea
precisely any more convoluted convoluted
cases where a function has several exit
points like several return statements
the idea would be to read them and try
to have a feeling for what they have in
common
so so that would indicate what this
function is returning and the end of a
function in most cases that's the end of
its source code but in some cases which
are more complicated the end of the
function is not at the end of the code
at the end of a function is more like
the output of the function and I think
that's what you want to figure out and
it can be returning or it can be like
you know you can pass a an output
parameter a function which is like your
variable you'll pass it so that the
function sets its result in two so that
counts as a quote code end or the
function performs a side effects then at
consonant as an output to so that's what
you want to look at first in your book
one thing I found interesting was you
had some techniques for dealing with
with functions that were very large so
if I wanted to understand a function
that just wouldn't fit on a screen of my
monitor because it's it's quite long how
many uh call that right it is a real
issue
they often should like your monitor is
has typically I don't know like I don't
know 50 hundred drawings likes even less
than that and our function there are
several hundreds of lines and even so
will thousands of lines and you hear of
those myths of like functions that are
like tens of thousands of lines but that
that exists you do have long functions
and if you if that function can't fit on
a screen and you can't look at it as a
whole and then you have to fit some of
it in your head while you're reading the
rest of it and that can be a challenge
so that's a great question well yeah
there are quite a few ways to tackle
that one but first you can start by
reading the end like we were saying
before now if it's so big it may be
doing several things so the end might be
just one of those so there's one
technique I I found like one day a
junior developer asked me like how I
could read code fast and you know when
you when you gain experience you just
read code faster and faster and you
don't always realize how we do that so I
try to like think I would realize what
exactly I was doing like what
subconscious reflex I I had allowed me
to to figure out a piece of code and I
found that I was looking for words that
came up frequently and even if like in
in just like a few lines of code or in
like hundreds of lines of code I think
that's some interesting indicator say
imagine for the for the sake of the
thought experiment that you're reading
just ten lines of code and say that is
code that is not immediate to figure out
and trust me there are some temp lines
of code that you can't figure out in
just a second
then what you want to know is what is
this code about you know like you
perhaps you have no idea what it's about
what is purpose what is doing if you if
you find a a term just a term I could be
the name of an object or a term that
comes up often in the function that are
called in that piece of code then you're
having it's a clue about what's it's
about right and if you know what it's
about then you can have this hypothesis
about what it's about
and if paper if this just happens to be
true and often it happens to be true
then all the rest clicks into place you
know and it's suddenly make sense and
that's how you can figure out that quite
quickly now it's easy to do for a
handful of lines because you can you can
have them within your sight but if you
have this vast function of I know yeah
say you 2009 for example there's no way
I mean for me there's no way I can scan
it and like scroll down on and on and
remember what whereas I've seen and
trying to figure out which one I've seen
most more than others
so I think you can make this analysis
more systematic by using a program that
would count the words of your code for
you that would make a report of the most
frequent words and like how how frequent
they were in a given piece of code so if
you if you feed a function to that
program it will tell you what the Stars
are you know I mean and if you feel
either file it will tell you this file
is mostly about such and such concepts
and now you want what a file is about
it's really useful so that would be how
high I would approach a long function if
I can't modify it so it's almost like
making an index right like the index of
a book you're saying yeah exactly
but but in sorted order oh because the
frequency is them is the important thing
fries yeah yeah I think about two things
at least two things are that interesting
to monitor one is the frequency so you
want to sort them by descending order
and another measure I found interesting
is the span everywhere by span I mean I
mean that's not a term invented isn't
common term programming it's the
distance between the first occurrence
and the last occurrence of that term
this turns in terms of lines of code if
you see a word that comes up frequently
and that has a small span that means
that there's a region a local portion of
your function that's intensive with that
term and that's an interesting tonight
because that would mean that this funk
this portion of the function is like I
mean you can mentally represent that
it's like a sub function it's like a sub
part of your function and that helps
mapping out what a function dowse by
having these small regions are focused
about one specific thing yeah it's it's
like a refactoring opportunity almost
exactly yeah that's a refactoring
opportunity actually this kind of
program I could I could test how this
kind of program because I wrote one and
if if like a listener is interested to
run
it's his their code with you can find
one on fluency be p.com
slash word - counts and we can England I
know show notes definitely definitely
so another thing that's in your book you
you advocate for developing an ability
to critique legacy code and in depth to
have to have specific feedback about
what's wrong with it
why why is that a useful skill it's
useful skill it's very useful skill and
I'm going to explain why
it's also a dangerous skill I think
let's start where they explaining why
it's that you as for where you look a
piece of codes that you have written a
while ago all that someone else has
written something that it's not fresh
for you it happens and if you're soft
wait a bit about you know that it
happens that it doesn't look quite right
to you like it feels like it's badly
written and when you see that you have
two choices I think one of them icing
this is bat code and move on and the
second choice is to try to express why
this is bad code because it happens that
you know this this this piece of code is
not world design but you can't quite
place a finger about on what exactly is
wrong with it and sometimes it takes a
bit of time of reflection and arises to
exactly pinpoint what's wrong with that
piece of code and being able to to
critique this this code in depth by in
depth I mean being able to to voice
exactly in in excruciating details why
you didn't like it
once you find that when you you identify
what's wrong with it you can you know
what to pay attention to you know that
that's specific aspect of design you
know it's important because it made you
feel uncomfortable in the first place
and next time you're going to write your
own code then you know you know you know
need to pay attention to that so by
doing this kind of analysis you get
better as a programmer I often compare
that with a VAX in
you know vats in in in like a medical
facts in while you get a short of a
disease but that's not dangerous and and
your body has time to nut is it or not
and rise it and do its stuff for the
immune system with antibodies or
whatever and then your body remembers it
it remembers exactly what's wrong with
that molecule however and the if if you
happen to actually encounter the ash
or disease then your body is going to
recognize it and and smash it apart in
no time and I think that energy is is
fine for bad code as well because if you
spend time to in a nice walk
why bad code is bad then you you won't
write bad code for that particular
aspect and you will recognize it easily
now yeah I was gonna say it's also
dangerous thing to do to critique or
rather to criticise code because by
going back to legacy code that's
something that people don't like I mean
as a natural reaction people don't like
existing code that that that if fear is
badly designed and some thumb it's
better designs events not badly design
and it's more difficult than it looks
but it's not really point a an important
message I'm trying to get across and my
book in my blog or everywhere is that
you should not complain if you don't
improve too if you do if you don't ton
intend to improve the code so you don't
criticize just for the sake of it
because it's a natural thing to do and
if you saw by saying oh this code is
terrible oh I would have them such a
better job and you do that all day then
you're going to get depressed and you're
going to press everyone who sits around
you so I think you gain it to be careful
to criticize only for learning purposes
or improving the code you feel that
there's a proper attitude that people
should bring to working on legacy code I
think so yes I was lucky to learn that
very early on in my career and I try to
repeat that every person I have in my
team and every every every time I can
really if you have to work with codes it
could be bad bit the one you rose or
beat some the one that someone else
wrote think about sets as your code if
you're working on it this is your code
you have to take ownership and if even
if you don't think it it's good even if
you didn't if you didn't write it
yourself this is your code and when you
get into that mindset you have the
position as a leader
you know you you feel empowered to do to
do things with this code because this is
your code so it doesn't matter that it's
bad you have to make the most of it and
you when you've when you take the
ownership over the code you're working
on
you leave this victim attitude fooling
that that's one one thing that's
particularly frustrating with legacy
code is when you feel like you're
bearing the consequences of someone who
made a poor design in the past and it's
it's not true you know because wealth in
the first place maybe that percent
didn't make it poor design maybe just
not seeing the big picture and maybe
even I mean in the same situation you
wouldn't wouldn't have them such a
better job but more importantly yeat
empowers you to do great things and you
can do fantastic things with legacy
codes so if we approach it with the
right attitude and we are going to make
a change to some code and so we come up
we we come up with a useful critique of
it actually what are some examples of
something that you would consider like a
useful critique of code as opposed to
just having the wrong attitude oh that
would be any critique that's technical
like them and once again for the sake of
improving the code or for the sake of
your learning one thing that comes up
very often is levels of abstraction I
think that's like the main thing in
programming you've had to some of the
best practices in three word that would
be those levels of abstraction that's
something that's sometimes not respected
and that makes the could to code the
code look bad and complicated I'm just
going to quickly describe what I mean by
a level of abstraction so if we go back
to our example of a call stack you know
I've got function functions calling
functions if you look at a particular
layer in that stack that defines a level
of abstraction a level of abstraction is
defined by what you're doing
and to go down to a lower level of
abstraction that corresponds to the
question how are you doing it and that
would be one step deeper deeper is some
a bit ambiguous but towers the top of
the call stack that's the low element of
structure and when you have so that's
that that's easy to see what the course
site but it's everywhere in programming
like you have a class then the interface
is a given level abstraction because
this is what the class is doing and the
implementation of the methods is a lower
level because it's how the class is
doing what it's doing and it's
absolutely everywhere so so sometimes
you have some low-level code code that
explains how it's doing stuff that's in
a place where it should mention what it
is doing and that's why offloading go to
stop functions officer is so useful
because you can replace a chunk of code
with her just to label this that's just
one kind of thing you can notice in a in
a piece of code and that's like one of
the first thing you get to notice now
when you get more and more in depth you
could notice very smaller things say
like the names of your parameters for
example in the function that don't
respect the correct level of abstraction
because for example they have names that
resemble something that's inside the
function inside of the function is
instead of what the function is doing as
a whole like how this parameter
participated to what the function is
doing from the point of view earth of
somebody that caused it so you were
saying a mistake people could make is is
having the parameters named incorrectly
could you explain that sure so when you
have to choose a name of a parameter or
anything else really but let's let's
stick to the parameters example that's a
tricky thing to do
that's like naming is is a difficult
thing to get right in programming
surprisingly I think that to get the
right name you have to choose the name
that's at
right level of abstraction and to do
that in practice you have to think about
what this object trying to name
represents it may sound a bit trivial
but this question what this what is this
object representing I think it's the
crux of how to get to do good naming for
easy example of the parameter if you
name your parameter with a name that
reflects how it participates to the
inside of the function but then you know
you're too low in terms of levels of
attraction because the parameter
represents something that's at the same
level as the name of the function how we
participate to them this this function
how it how it must it must sound like
something logical to pass this function
if it looks like something that's
logical to implement a function that
then it's too low and on the other hand
if you're too high in terms of level of
abstraction for a parameter that your
parameter is bound to the context of the
function the context that uses that
function and and that's the natural
thing to do because sometimes you're
creating a functions for this for the
purpose of using it in one place so the
only example of naming you have is is
the the surrounding naming surrounding
core the core surrounding the core site
now the second time you're going to use
that function you're going to look at
its interface and and sometimes it's not
going to fit with the new context and
when this happens you know that the
parameter has a name that's too high in
terms of abstraction because it's it's
connected with the other context and
then I think a good thing to do in that
case is to go back to your parameter
think about a better name that would fit
for both context and then you have
something that's closer the level of
abstraction of the interface does this
make sense I think I think I understand
so I'm thinking of if I I have some
function that is called let's say format
email and it takes in a string and it
goes through and it removes any like
double line breaks right and I call it
that because I use it to format my email
so that is kind of a violation of this
levels right because it doesn't actually
format an email I'm giving it to
specific of a name what it's actually
should be called to something like
remove extra line breaks exactly and
your parameter should we call email but
should be cool text for example and
that's an example that's that's a great
example because it's um it shows
immediately but there are more tricky
ones that you see in day to day code and
that are not so so well defined and you
have to think hard about about them you
know yeah digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size removing
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software the customers love
with thousands of in-depth tutorials and
an active community we provide the
support you need digitalocean stands out
of the crowd due to its simplicity and
high performance with no billing
surprises try digitalocean for free by
getting a 100 dollar infrastructure
credit at doco /se radio so one thing I
was thinking about reading your book if
we if we need to learn to develop skills
at finding what's wrong with legacy code
but yet you're saying you know 95
percent of code is legacy like where do
we where do we see better code where do
we learn what good code looks like well
so uh a few paces places you can read
good code and if you do read good code
you're going to develop an and an
unconscious model for good patterns and
when you're going to read when you're
going to read your legacy codes some
things are going to jump out to you
because they are not going to match the
patterns you've learned by reading good
codes you know it's like reading good
English like if you'll read she'll read
good English often and then you're wrote
in English it's going to improve so
where do you find good codes well one
example is to read codes that uses the
standard library of your language the
standard library that's shipped with
language
typically helps you accomplish things
with concise go that's a great way to
improve to yet raise levels of
Attraction really so reading code that
use that uses your standard library is a
good example now where can you find such
code well I think you have several
places one of them is like on the
Internet you've got write blogs for
example so teach you how to use your
standard rivalry with code examples and
you can like see the pattern if right
for the sake of C++ for example or I
don't know how many C++ developers out
there today but like if you go on
frequency PP dot gum slash STL you see
like a collection of articles showing
how to use it's done memory now you can
also look for standard library usages in
your code base for example and and when
you stumble upon them try and think if
you like that code and if you like that
give it that's a good example now doing
a bit like more generic than the
standard library you can read code that
uses libraries in general there are some
languages have some canonical libraries
that extend the language and like push
it forward and do amazing things with
them like another C++ example I'm sorry
I'm a bit C++ oriented but in simplifies
that would be boost for example if
you're a super expressive about you
probably know what boost Susan if you
don't know just go and boost boost org
and you know everything about it and
boost pushes the language forward and
does amazing things and if you go and
boost documentation or on boost books
for example if you're interested I can
give you some references you can put in
the show note you you'll see what things
you can do with C++ that you never
dreamed about doing so that would be a
new patterns you'll see and that you can
use in your interfaces
other places you can read you can you
can try and and get some info about
what's coming up in your language before
we leave boost and
so do you have an example of something
that you have learned this helped your
work with legacy code that you've
learned from from boost well yeah one of
my favorite boost libraries is the
ranges and so the range is is a bit like
if you're a Java developer I think
that's a new thing
what happened a few years ago that's
called streams and I think a lot of
languages have that Python have that has
that I can't remember the name so it's
about performing operations on
collections and chaining up these
operations like you've got your
collection and you send that through
some sort of component that would apply
function to every element of your
collection and you send the result of
that to another component that will I
will filter for example on a predicate
and you send that to a third component
that would do another basic thing and
all put together you can have a look at
modular toolbox to city operations on
your collections and so code that uses
that is absolutely beautiful and
actually this went a bit further in C++
because there was a famous library that
went further than that which is called
range V tree and it will be in C++ 20
and this I learnt it in boost for a
start and I used to use that in my code
and wow that really makes a difference
be there in negative code or in your
hobby code event to handle collections
so because of that you're able to to
take the legacy code and use some of
those techniques which makes it easier
to understand or change absolutely yeah
so that that's an example right of of
going into some legacy code and
improving it so should we just you know
jump in and improve things whenever we
get the chance when we're working in a
legacy code base oh no absolutely not I
don't think so
the thing is it would be great in theory
if you could fix the world that would be
awesome but the thing is legacy code
base tend to be vast one thing that
makes codes go into legacy codes is age
you know like if you have old code it
has more chances to be legacy than like
brand new code you just ship mmm it
doesn't mean that every old piece of
code is legacy but you know there's a
strand of ya old projects that have code
that's difficult to work with and if a
project has time to grow old then it has
had time to grow big so a legacy code
base can be fast really and in a vast
codebase are a million things that could
be improved so there's I think there's
no way you can fix everything and make
every last line of code absolutely
perfect in your legacy code base I think
that's something you need to realize and
and it's ok you know
and it's great thing that's ok and I
think one way to see that is the 8020
rule if you know what I'm referring to
but at some this proportion yeah that
this proportion that some seems to be
there in pretty much every domain I
think it originated in economics with
perrito's observing that in a society
was it yeah 20% of the people held 80
percent of the wealth and this 20 a C
can be generalized in 20% of the causes
trigger 80% of the consequences and the
typical application in programming is
for performance like 20% of the
execution time your program is spent in
80% of your code so there's only if you
bottlenecks you need to focus on but
that's not our topic and I think this
this spirit can apply a knife it's
exactly a sip sense or 90 or 70 I don't
know but I'm sure that all the code is
not equal and that really shows at any
scale even if you look like at a
function you're going to see that all
lines don't matter there are just a
handful of lines that really contains
some meaningful action and and I think
that's true for like larger scales I
give code base there are some
places where you go everywhere ever all
the time everyone goes there all this
time that's the places that are hot if I
may say in terms like of cash cash for
Camry
it's the places that people change
they make fixes because that bugs or
because our interesting and the clients
want more features in them and those
paths they represent a portion of your
codebase and this is the portion that
matter and when you think crudely about
it what is the purpose of having good
code like really we say that good code
is a great thing but why is that is it
like like a good thing with Mehran I
don't think so the point of code is to
make a piece of software run and and to
make it run in a way that what make
customers happy and that's a very harsh
business view but I think that's what
code is for in I mean in a professional
context of course so making code Goods
has to somehow impure improve your
business so if you make code better it
can be because better code tends to have
less bugs or because it's easier to add
features to better code that it is to
code that you can't make any sense of
and that that's quite a natural thing to
think about
so you need to figure out where is this
code and that's where that's where you
want to focus your efforts and to think
about it there's this framework I use
all the time I mean it's very simple
things but that's where X it's a value
cost analysis if you want to take an
action it will bring your value now you
want to improve some code I would bring
your value mmm and I will cost you
something I would cost you mainly time
and time is a finite resource so every
time you want to make a brief factoring
task think about how much would it bring
and how much would it cost and when you
think this way some things become
obvious like for example you you
shouldn't do a refactoring project just
because it's easy to do or just because
it doesn't cost a lot like I hear
people's
time say I'm gonna go in that code and
and improve I don't know like the names
or make the code cleaner and and that's
an easy thing to do you know and if no
one goes through that code that doesn't
matter is it's it's it's the same thing
as fixing some others company code you
know that won't make you better I want I
won't make you a business better because
there's no value you're saying the cost
is low but the value is there's zero
absolutely that's exactly my point
now I'm not saying that naming is that
thing that naming is tremendously
important but that matters more in code
that matters
I assume another concern could be people
go into some code that they they don't
understand like per your definition they
obviously don't understand some aspect
of it if it's legacy and then rewrite it
like how do they know that they've
actually made it better or that they
haven't introduced new bugs or etc right
well I think that's that's two questions
how is it better and are there new books
how is it better in terms of design well
I think that's that ties up well with
what we were talking about before about
think about why code is bad well your
piece of code is bad like being very
meticulous in your analysis I think you
can do the same kind of analysis after
the fact like when you did choose to fix
a piece of code like to improve its
quality by making a refactoring task
after it I think it's a great thing not
to move on immediately but rather to
think about why it's better and once
again once again it's not something
that's obvious to do sometimes like for
example I remember one time where we had
a slightly complicated if statement like
something that was and if involving
several billions and a bit of nesting
you know nothing
monstrous but you know the thing that
takes you a few minutes to figure out
and we were thinking well this this if
we see it often maybe we should do
something about it so we went about and
and refracted it and we moved it around
and somehow it was looking much better
much easier to understand and
and then we stopped then thought why is
that
why is it better you know it looks
better I feel I can understand it better
and that's the point of code really but
what is that and after after a few I
know like minutes apps or perhaps even
more I don't remember maybe an hour of
analysis or perhaps like when you think
about when you sleep on it
really sometimes it's come as a few days
after when you do something else in
between we realized it was better
because it was sticking to the
specification like the business had
explained us if such-and-such condition
are met within this context and without
this other I don't know special feature
feature then we should do that thing you
know and and after the refactoring our
if statement was looking exactly like
that and surprisingly it was more nested
my nested I mean when there is an if
system statement inside of an if
statement and you can measure nesting
with the indentation which is the
distance from the left margin of your
screen
you know there's this this general
guideline about if statement that's
classical thing in programming which is
avoid nesting like like refactor your if
statement so that there are as little
nested as possible if if can be not
nested at all and in this particular
case the the if statement became more
nested but Clara and I was because it it
sticks is stick it stuck better at the
specification so we came up with that
guideline that we try to use every time
we have to do something that's related
to a conditional try to stick to the
specification to what the business side
more than about nesting and that's it
uses useful thing to tonight so that's
for your first question about how do you
know it's better you have to think about
it you have to like understand the
details and you can because it's all
technical now how do you know if it's it
has if it has more bugs well for one
thing if it's more understandable it's
less likely to have bugs because the
more you understand the more you will
see the bugs now more yeah down-to-earth
thing is tests really if you have tests
around a piece of code then you have you
can have more confidence that you didn't
break anything because if you did break
something that is covered by your tests
then your tests will fail and you'll
know immediately so that's um yeah
that's something that's allows you to
move forward tests I like to this
example the structural indenting so
following the rule very clearly about
reducing indent actually would lead you
to a solution that was less good than
what you ended up with exactly the rules
it's not it's not totally rule-based but
you should be able to explain it so now
you have to know that nesting is
something that can be dangerous that's a
smell but performing your analysis on on
your codes allows you to go further
expand beyond the rules and that's like
you know I am another level with skills
you know I mean yeah like you have to
have the basics but then from there
there's more required yeah right
in your experience what percentage of
work on legacy code is new features
versus bugs and maintenance there's this
so I think it depends on on projects and
companies and people but the safe
framework which is an extension of the
agile methodology advocates for a 30 70
percent proportion so that would be 30
percent for maintenance and 70 percent
for new features and people use safe
with the existing code and Nega secured
so I think that's a valid target for
legacy code and then if we are this
junior developer who's new to working in
a legacy code base and we need to work
on some sort of bug fix for a legacy
code base how how would I approach that
well yeah that's a question that I think
every developer has asked or wondered at
the beginning of its of their career the
natural thing to do is to go look at the
code mmm because if there's a bug then
that means that there's something wrong
in the code so you want to go find it
that's that's basically your mission and
that's actually sure you want that's
true that's what you want to do you want
to find what's wrong in the code but
surprisingly the fastest way
at least the fastest way I know is not
to look at the code the fastest way I
know is well start by making sure you
can reproduce a problem on your
environments and that's that's not
always a given and once you do then you
still don't look at the codes you look
at the application and well there's a
like a step by step process that correct
that I described in my book but the gist
of it is is that you want to reduce your
use case like you've got a bug you've
got a bug report saying this feature
doesn't work properly and you want to
know if it's exactly these feature that
has a problem or perhaps just a subset
of it or perhaps something that's
connected with it so you try and and and
test for other use cases that are close
to your initial use case and and at some
point you're going to stop reproducing
and you'll know some sort of like the
border between the place of the code
where you produce and the place where
you don't reproduce and that that shows
a smaller part of the application which
is actually concerned with the bug and
once you have this small portion you can
formulate a hypothesis about what is
wrong and only then you can go and open
up your your debugger and look at the
code just to make sure if you got it
right just spice by testing the
application if you got it right not
awesome
that's how you finally found you found
the cause of the bug and if you didn't
then you make another hypothesis and
really that speeds up the code the you
know this is so much I like to compare
that with the binary search because
that's something that programmers can
relate to you know when you have to look
at something to look for something in a
collection that is sorted then you have
two ways there's no way in the fast way
the slow way consists in in checking the
first element and if it's not the one
you're searching for then you check the
second one
and and so on and you're going to check
potentially as many elements are there
in the collection and binary search
consists in in checking right in the
middle and if it's not the one you're
looking for then you see if what you
found is smaller a bigger and
accordingly go left or right and so on
and you converge in in logarithmic time
which is like literally orders of
magnitude magnitude faster and I think
that's about the same thing with with
with bug finding because if you look at
the codes then you're going to start to
read goat and you're going to start to
read line by line
hopefully faster with a speed reading
techniques we've mentioned and that
detail or in my book but you're gonna
have to go through some codes but if you
just test out some some use cases in the
application it's like locating the place
you want to look for just like you would
be locating that place when you do
binary search and that's way faster it's
one thing and that's also way more fun
because yeah because you've got this
process that works most of the time I'm
not saying it works hundred percent the
times because you've got like some weird
bug sometimes but most of the time it
works very splendidly and you know it's
just a matter of time before you find it
so when you do that your maintenance is
a bit like a game you know and and
that's stimulating because it makes you
think and so using your brain is very
motivating thing when you're programming
and yeah it goes faster and it's more
fun and why it is important to have
hypotheses because if you don't you
don't know what you're looking for and
if you don't know what you're looking
for you're going to look at the code and
look for something's wrong you know and
chances are you're going to find
something wrong but not what's what's
causing your book or you going to find
something that looks wrong and that's
not actually wrong and not related and
you're going to go into
tracts and you can you can go far and
and waste time in on trucks if you have
a hypothesis on the other hand you know
exactly you the the answer you want you
have a question you want an answer and
and you know everything in the go that's
not related to your question yeah that
makes sense and so you you're trying to
disprove or or prove your hypothesis as
you're clicking around that's the that's
the guiding principle precisely so do
you advise like creating documentation
as part of understanding legacy code or
how do we how do we work with the system
without documentation how do we build up
the knowledge yes what you just said I
think it's an important thing
documenting helps understanding right
you can create understanding out of
nowhere with documentation that's very
surprising thing to know to do because
it's it sounds like magic but the very
facts of explaining what you already
understood helps you understand more you
you probably know that if you have made
a talk or written a blog post or written
a book or written actually a piece of
documentation if you explain anything to
anyone in any form and I'm sure every
listener date at some point you know
that this make you this this this made
you realize things and if anything else
it helps you realize that there are
things you didn't know there are holes
in your understanding and that gives you
more questions to answer to make it
consistent whole so that's just one
aspect of how documenting helps
understanding yes that's a great example
because you you're saying that the
actual act of explaining it to somebody
via documentation actually deepens your
understanding it's a way to for you to
understand it better and of course it
goes without saying that it helps the
other people oh it's going are going to
read your documentation now I think yeah
when you're a software developer doing
mentleman documentation is not hype last
No
the thing that motivates people becoming
developers where I list it what I've met
that's why I think it's important to
realize how important it is and that
it's not a a terrible thing today and
one way to this to see things that I've
realized over time by actually managing
people when making them write
documentation is documentation just like
improving good quality you don't do it
because you don't do it because it's a
good thing you know you don't you don't
do it because you're a good person you
do it because it helps the business and
knowing that you you're going to quit
this horrible it's horrible for everyone
attitude where you write documentation
like you we do homework you know like my
manager asked me to do that I don't have
a choice I'm going to crank it out and
and be done with it and that's the worst
documentation you can make for you for
everyone for you because it's going to
be pain and for everyone because it
shows really when you read a piece of
documentation that's been written up at
someone that didn't want to write it
that just just cranked it out it shows
and you don't really understand then
it's not helpful and if he's not helpful
then you're wasted your time you know
yeah that's a great attitude yeah so one
simple tip I was going to say when you
write documentation is to choices not
because you have to because you're
because you're you've been asked to or
because you feel guilty not to write it
to explain something you had a hard time
understanding explain it to your past
self you know because you know how it
feels not to understand that thing you
know what's easier to understand you
know what's like the tribbles
and and it sounded like you were
speaking yet your past self because
other people are like your past self
they don't know about it and actually
your future self has a high chance to be
like you power self at some point
definitely true so I'm really enjoying
your book John
then one question I had about it was
what made you choose the perspective so
it seems to be written very much from
the perspective of from a practitioners
perspective somebody who's just been sat
down in front of a giant code basin and
has to work with it does that come from
your personal experience or yeah a lot
of it does I've been a software
developers for Kepler years now like
eight years I yeah I've worked my way up
I'm currently a team lead and I tried to
reflect on why I was loving my job and
how I progressed since I began because
when I began I didn't know anything
pretty much
I had no idea what legacy could was
right I'm not saying that because I'm
work at the code I'm work you know is
it's terrible is it's I mean I can't say
much about that but it's it's not
because I had a horror story
quite the contrary actually I noticed
that people around me like the people I
met like a meet-up or on the internet or
whatever they were sad about about the
code they were working with and I think
it's a terrible thing because most of us
we choose our job out of fashion mmm
you know quite a few developers have
been programming before they were
actually working as a developer legacy
code is everywhere so I was trying to to
convey to people how to be happy we have
their job because it's a fascinating
thing to be programming we do you know
that
so how to be happy and how to make the
most of it had to be efficient how to
how to be successful how to get better I
had to be happy every day and make
fantastic things with your code and I
think this book I hope this book will
change how people will see their
everyday life with working with existing
code well I think that's a great
attitude and also a great place to end
so where can listeners get your book
it's available online pub so you can get
it at lean PubCon slash legacy code and
output
I'll put a link in the show notes so
Jonathan thanks for coming on the show
thanks for having me
yeah it's been fun this is Adam Gordon
bail for software engineering radio
thank you for listening
thanks for listening the SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
Archer police software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website @ SC - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com
you can also email us at team @ SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
se radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening